<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../AOML/AOML.xsl"?>

<observation-set xmlns="http://vortex.cis.vtc.edu/xml/AOML_0.0"
  xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://vortex.cis.vtc.edu/xml/AOML_0.0 ../AOML/AOML.xsd">

  <datetime>
    <date>2002-08-31-04:00</date>
  </datetime>
  <location>
    <value>
      <lat-long-alt>+43.00-072.50+300</lat-long-alt>
    </value>
    <notes>
      <xhtml:p>US-Vermont-Tunbridge</xhtml:p>
    </notes>
  </location>
  <observer>Peter C. Chapin</observer>
  <equipment>
    <notes>
      <xhtml:p>75mm Unitron refractor with 25mm (48x) eyepiece.</xhtml:p>
    </notes>
  </equipment>
  <notes>
    <xhtml:p>It was excellently clear this evening with magnitude 5.9 stars "easily" visible in
      Cygnus. If anything the conditions tonight were better than during my last observing
      session.</xhtml:p>

    <xhtml:p>My plan for the evening was to look at open clusters in Cepheus, including some
      rather faint ones. Finding such objects is always a bit of a challenge against a rich
      Milky Way background. Faint star associations can look like a diffuse object to averted
      vision so false alarms and self-misleading observations are always a danger.</xhtml:p>
  </notes>

  <observation>
    <object>
      <id catalog="NGC" id="7235"/>
      <type>cluster/open</type>
      <constellation>Cep</constellation>
    </object>
    <notes>
      <xhtml:p>This cluster was easy to locate since it was involved with the triangle formed by
        delta, zeta, and epsilon Cephei. It was relatively compact and has a bright (probably
        foreground) star involved. Averted vision showed some of the member stars, but it was
        obvious that many remain unresolved. Despite the rich field the cluster still stood out
        fairly well. Nice view.</xhtml:p>
    </notes>
  </observation>

  <observation>
    <object>
      <id catalog="NGC" id="7281"/>
      <type>cluster/open</type>
      <constellation>Cep</constellation>
    </object>
    <notes>
      <xhtml:p>I couldn't confirm a sighting of this object. I did see a suspicious foggy area
        in the right location but the richness of the Milky Way background made it difficult for
        me to be sure it was the cluster. I did notice a line of four fairly bright stars in a
        distinct row involved with my suspect cluster. That would be something to look for again
        in a larger instrument. This object was also easy to locate because it was in the same
        distinctive triangle as NGC-7235.</xhtml:p>
    </notes>
  </observation>

  <observation>
    <object xsi:type="starMultipleObjectType">
      <id catalog="ADS" id="15987"/>
      <name>Delta Cephei</name>
      <type>star/multiple</type>
      <constellation>Cep</constellation>
      <component designation="A">
        <magnitude>3.5-4.4</magnitude>
      </component>
      <component designation="B">
        <magnitude>7.5</magnitude>
      </component>
      <separation designation-1="A" designation-2="B" distance="41.0"/>
    </object>
    <notes>
      <xhtml:p>I couldn't help but notice this nice double as I scanned around the vicinity. The
        primary is one of the most famous variable stars in the sky (the prototype Cepheid
        variable). The secondary was quite far from the primary&#x2014;easily split with my
        25mm&#x2014;and it had a bluish color making for a striking contrast.</xhtml:p>
    </notes>
  </observation>

  <observation>
    <object>
      <id catalog="NGC" id="7261"/>
      <type>cluster/open</type>
      <constellation>Cep</constellation>
    </object>
    <notes>
      <xhtml:p>This cluster was right near a somewhat bright star. It showed up pretty easily in
        the 'scope although the rich background made the view a bit tricky. With direct vision
        the cluster appeared as a dusky patch. Averted vision showed a number of member stars
        and more fuzz as well. Nice view.</xhtml:p>
    </notes>
  </observation>

  <observation>
    <object>
      <id catalog="NGC" id="7160"/>
      <type>cluster/open</type>
      <constellation>Cep</constellation>
    </object>
    <notes>
      <xhtml:p>This cluster was involved with a fairly bright star so it was easy to find. In
        the finder 'scope the cluster looked like a fuzzy star. This was not a particular
        dramatic looking object. Direct vision showed several fairly bright stars collected
        together. Averted vision showed quite a few background stars as well, although glare
        from the foreground stars confused things a bit.</xhtml:p>
    </notes>
  </observation>

  <observation>
    <object>
      <id catalog="NGC" id="7142"/>
      <type>cluster/open</type>
      <constellation>Cep</constellation>
    </object>
    <notes>
      <xhtml:p>Nice view. In the 25mm this cluster looked like a ghostly fog with a few sugar
        sprinkles. There were some fairly bright stars near the object, but I suspect that they
        were not cluster members. Averted vision showed a few cluster members although mostly it
        remained diffuse. The cluster seemed fairly large.</xhtml:p>
    </notes>
  </observation>

  <observation>
    <object-group>
      <object>
        <id catalog="NGC" id="7129"/>
        <type>nebula</type>
        <constellation>Cep</constellation>
      </object>
      <object>
        <id catalog="NGC" id="7133"/>
        <type>nebula</type>
        <constellation>Cep</constellation>
      </object>
    </object-group>
    <notes>
      <xhtml:p>These clusters were plotted in SkyAtlas 2000 as diffuse nebula right near
        NGC-7142. I didn't expect to see them but to my surprise I was able to see a distinct
        fuzzy blob in the right location for NGC-7129 using the binoculars! I put the scope on
        the object and found a small cluster of a few stars surrounded by more fuzz than seems
        explainable by glare. When I later checked the NGC catalog I noticed that this object is
        listed as a "cluster + nebula". In retrospect I have to say that I was observing the
        object. It did not look particularly stunning, however. I didn't see anything that might
        have been NGC-7133 although I didn't look for it either.</xhtml:p>
    </notes>
  </observation>

  <observation>
    <object>
      <id catalog="NGC" id="7380"/>
      <type>cluster/open</type>
      <constellation>Cep</constellation>
    </object>
    <notes>
      <xhtml:p>This cluster was easy to find because it was right near a relatively bright star.
        The cluster showed up to some degree in the binoculars although it would have been
        difficult to confirm it as a cluster there. In the telescope, however, it was obvious.
        In fact, it was a nice object. Quite a few stars were resolving and there was clearly
        quite a few more that were not. Despite the rich field, the cluster stood out nicely.
        The cluster appeared to have a 'V' shape.</xhtml:p>
    </notes>
  </observation>

</observation-set>
