<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../AOML/AOML.xsl"?>

<observation-set xmlns="http://vortex.cis.vtc.edu/xml/AOML_0.0"
  xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://vortex.cis.vtc.edu/xml/AOML_0.0 ../AOML/AOML.xsd">

  <localdatetimerange>
    <start type="LST">
      <ISO>2002-11-19T04:45:00</ISO>
    </start>
    <end type="LST">
      <ISO>2002-11-19T05:15:00</ISO>
    </end>
  </localdatetimerange>
  <location>
    <value>
      <lat-long-alt>+43.00-072.50+300</lat-long-alt>
    </value>
    <notes>
      <xhtml:p>US-Vermont-Tunbridge</xhtml:p>
    </notes>
  </location>
  <observer>Peter C. Chapin</observer>
  <equipment>
    <notes>
      <xhtml:p>I observed with my unaided eyes tonight.</xhtml:p>
    </notes>
  </equipment>
  <notes>
    <xhtml:p>The Leonids!</xhtml:p>

    <xhtml:p>The sky conditions this morning were far from ideal. There was a full moon in the
      West and thin clouds covering most of the sky. The moon illuminated the clouds and washed
      out the sky background most effectively. In many parts of the sky only the major stars
      were visible although there were some relatively clear patches where the limiting
      magnitude might have been as good as 4<xhtml:sup>th</xhtml:sup>. The moon was rather far
      from the Leonid radiant (100 degrees?) and that was helpful. The temperature was well
      below freezing.</xhtml:p>

    <xhtml:p>I estimated that I saw somewhat more than one Leonid per minute. I'm guessing that
      I observed a rate of 100 per hour. I did not do any kind of formal count, however.
      Considering the conditions the shower was quite active although I doubt if the ZHR was
      several thousand per hour as some had predicted for this time.</xhtml:p>

    <xhtml:p>As I observed last year, some of the Leonids were rather faint and some were quite
      bright. This year I saw more bright ones than faint ones due, no doubt, to the sky
      conditions. On one occasion I happened to be looking directly at a rather bright Leonid
      as it flashed by. It was considerably brighter than Jupiter (conveniently placed in Leo as
      a comparison "star"). I'd estimate the meteor at magnitude -4. On another occasion, I was
      looking away from the meteor, but I knew a bright one had just happened because I could
      see the snow light up around me. When I turned I saw a thick "smoke trail" glowing
      brightly for a few seconds. It was located near the moon and may have been glowing, partly
      at least, from reflected moonlight.</xhtml:p>

    <xhtml:p>Overall it was a good show compared to most meteor showers, but not as impressive
      as what I observed last year and certainly not a meteor "storm".</xhtml:p>

  </notes>

</observation-set>
