<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../AOML/AOML.xsl"?>

<observation-set xmlns="http://vortex.cis.vtc.edu/xml/AOML_0.0"
  xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://vortex.cis.vtc.edu/xml/AOML_0.0 ../AOML/AOML.xsd">

  <datetime>
    <date>2002-08-20-04:00</date>
  </datetime>
  <location>
    <value>
      <lat-long-alt>+43.00-072.50+300</lat-long-alt>
    </value>
    <notes>
      <xhtml:p>US-Vermont-Tunbridge</xhtml:p>
    </notes>
  </location>
  <observer>Peter C. Chapin</observer>
  <equipment>
    <notes>
      <xhtml:p>75mm Unitron refractor with the following eyepieces: 25mm (48x), 18mm (67x), and
        12.5mm (96x). I also used 7x50 binoculars to help locate objects.</xhtml:p>
    </notes>
  </equipment>
  <notes>
    <xhtml:p>I've had my telescope (75mm Unitron refractor) in storage for over a year while my
      wife and I worked on some renovations around the house. I took it out of storage just a
      couple of days ago and set it up for easy access. Tonight was the first time I've used my
      scope in months. I had to rebalance it and realign the finder but basically it seemed to
      work fine.</xhtml:p>

    <xhtml:p>Tonight was clear, cool, and not nearly as hazy as it has been the last few nights.
      The moon was fat (only two days from full) and was washing out a good part of the sky.
      Limiting magnitude in Cyg, on zenith, was probably 4.5 (estimated). However, my targets
      tonight were double stars and they are not as affected by extra light as deep sky objects
      would have been.</xhtml:p>

    <xhtml:p>Note: The technical information on the doubles was taken from "Norton's 2000.0 Star
      Atlas and Reference Handbook"</xhtml:p>
  </notes>

  <observation>
    <object xsi:type="starMultipleObjectType">
      <id catalog="ADS" id="14279"/>
      <name>Gamma Del</name>
      <type>star/multiple</type>
      <constellation>Del</constellation>
      <component designation="A">
        <magnitude>4.5</magnitude>
      </component>
      <component designation="B">
        <magnitude>5.5</magnitude>
      </component>
      <separation designation-1="A" designation-2="B" distance="9.6"/>
    </object>
    <notes>
      <xhtml:p>Easily split in the 25mm. Nice view. The stars are close enough to be
        interesting, but not so close as to be difficult. The stars exhibited a nice color
        contrast. The brighter star was yellowish and the fainter one seemed to have a
        blue/white color.</xhtml:p>
    </notes>
  </observation>

  <observation>
    <object xsi:type="starMultipleObjectType">
      <id catalog="ADS" id="13442"/>
      <name>Theta Sge</name>
      <type>star/multiple</type>
      <constellation>Sge</constellation>
      <component designation="A">
        <magnitude>6.5</magnitude>
      </component>
      <component designation="B">
        <magnitude>9.0</magnitude>
      </component>
      <separation designation-1="A" designation-2="B" distance="11.9"/>
    </object>
    <notes>
      <xhtml:p>Looks like a wide double in the finder. However, in the 25mm eyepiece shows that
        the brighter star of the "finder double" is the actual double of interest (Theta). The
        companion is quite a bit fainter than the primary but still easy to see.</xhtml:p>
    </notes>
  </observation>

  <observation>
    <object xsi:type="starMultipleObjectType">
      <id catalog="ADS" id="13765"/>
      <name>Gamma Cyg</name>
      <type>star/multiple</type>
      <constellation>Cyg</constellation>
      <component designation="A">
        <magnitude>2.2</magnitude>
      </component>
      <component designation="B">
        <magnitude>9.5</magnitude>
      </component>
      <separation designation-1="A" designation-2="B" distance="41.2"/>
    </object>
    <notes>
      <xhtml:p>Right in the middle of the cross. Despite the wide separation I was not able to
        confirm a sighting of the secondary. I used a variety of magnifications. The secondary
        might be too faint to see with direct vision but averted vision increased the glare from
        the primary considerably and could easily bury the much fainter secondary.</xhtml:p>
    </notes>
  </observation>

  <observation>
    <object>
      <id catalog="NGC" id="6910"/>
      <type>cluster/open</type>
      <constellation>Cyg</constellation>
    </object>
    <notes>
      <xhtml:p>This cluster is immediately to the north of Gamma Cyg and so I thought I might as
        well check it out while I was in the area. Averted vision showed a clear enrichment of
        the sky background in one particular spot in the right vicinity (using 25mm eyepiece).
        There were several bright foreground stars and a sense of many additional stars just out
        of reach. This object might look very interesting in a larger scope or on a more
        suitable night.</xhtml:p>
    </notes>
  </observation>

  <observation>
    <object xsi:type="starMultipleObjectType">
      <id catalog="ADS" id="14259"/>
      <name>52 Cyg</name>
      <type>star/multiple</type>
      <constellation>Cyg</constellation>
      <component designation="A">
        <magnitude>4.2</magnitude>
      </component>
      <component designation="B">
        <magnitude>9.4</magnitude>
      </component>
      <separation designation-1="A" designation-2="B" distance="6.0"/>
    </object>
    <notes>
      <xhtml:p>Unable to resolve. I used several different magnifications (25mm, 18mm, 12.5mm,
        9mm). I'm sure the large difference in magnitudes was the problem. I had hoped that I
        would have more luck with this than with Gamma Cyg since the primary isn't quite as
        bright. However, the two stars are also much closer together. Note that this star is
        involved with one branch of the Veil Nebula (it often shows up very brightly in pictures
        of the Veil). Of course I was not able to see the Veil Nebula tonight!</xhtml:p>
    </notes>
  </observation>

  <observation>
    <object xsi:type="starMultipleObjectType">
      <id catalog="ADS" id="14158"/>
      <name>49 Cyg</name>
      <type>star/multiple</type>
      <constellation>Cyg</constellation>
      <component designation="A">
        <magnitude>5.7</magnitude>
      </component>
      <component designation="B">
        <magnitude>7.8</magnitude>
      </component>
      <separation designation-1="A" designation-2="B" distance="2.7"/>
    </object>
    <notes>
      <xhtml:p>Unable to resolve. I expected this one to be tough in my 75mm Unitron. Although
        the separation is reasonable, the difference in magnitude, while not extreme, is enough
        to be difficult when the stars are that close. I took a hard look at the star, however,
        using all eyepieces up to the 6mm. I could see 49 Cyg as a small, well focused disk
        surrounded by three clear diffraction rings. The seeing tonight was quite good; even at
        high magnification the star image held steady. However, I could not see the secondary. I
        did notice some brightening in one side of the diffraction rings at times, but the rings
        are not uniform anyway (my 'scope isn't perfect... what can I say) and I wasn't able to
        confirm a sighting.</xhtml:p>
    </notes>
  </observation>

  <observation>
    <object xsi:type="starMultipleObjectType">
      <id catalog="ADS" id="14636"/>
      <name>61 Cyg</name>
      <type>star/multiple</type>
      <constellation>Cyg</constellation>
      <component designation="A">
        <magnitude>5.2</magnitude>
      </component>
      <component designation="B">
        <magnitude>6.0</magnitude>
      </component>
      <separation designation-1="A" designation-2="B" distance="30.3"/>
    </object>
    <notes>
      <xhtml:p>Wide and easy. I was able to split this double in the finder. The stars have
        about equal magnitudes and both look a bit reddish. Averted vision gave me the
        impression that there was a cluster nearby. I seemed to see a faint group of stars just
        to the side of 61 Cyg. There is nothing plotted in any of my atlases so it was probably
        just a bit of rich Milky Way background.</xhtml:p>
    </notes>
  </observation>

</observation-set>
