<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!DOCTYPE entry-set [
  <!-- Mozilla does not process external entities.
  <!ENTITY % AOMLentities SYSTEM "AOML.ent">
  %AOMLentities;
  -->

<!-- Useful symbols. -->
<!ENTITY copy     "&#169;">

<!-- Greek. Needed for star names. -->
<!ENTITY alpha    "&#945;">
<!ENTITY beta     "&#946;">
<!ENTITY gamma    "&#947;">
<!ENTITY delta    "&#948;">
<!ENTITY epsilon  "&#949;">
<!ENTITY zeta     "&#950;">
<!ENTITY eta      "&#951;">
<!ENTITY theta    "&#952;">
<!ENTITY iota     "&#953;">
<!ENTITY kappa    "&#954;">
<!ENTITY lambda   "&#955;">
<!ENTITY mu       "&#956;">
<!ENTITY nu       "&#957;">
<!ENTITY xi       "&#958;">
<!ENTITY omicron  "&#959;">
<!ENTITY pi       "&#960;">
<!ENTITY rho      "&#961;">
<!ENTITY sigma    "&#963;">
<!ENTITY tau      "&#964;">
<!ENTITY upsilon  "&#965;">
<!ENTITY phi      "&#966;">
<!ENTITY chi      "&#967;">
<!ENTITY psi      "&#968;">
<!ENTITY omega    "&#969;">

]>

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../AOML/AOML.xsl"?>

<entry-set xmlns="http://vortex.cis.vtc.edu/xml/AOML_0.0"
  xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://vortex.cis.vtc.edu/xml/AOML_0.0 ../AOML/AOML.xsd">

  <entry>
    <localdatetime type="LST">
      <date>2016-01-13</date>
    </localdatetime>

    <text>
      <xhtml:h1>Quick Look From Meadow Run</xhtml:h1>

      <xhtml:p>I observed from Meadow Run Road a little ways before the entrance to Forest Run.
        There is a space between two streetlights where the road is unlit and relatively dark. I
        was out between 7:30 and 8:00pm in cold weather.</xhtml:p>

      <xhtml:p>I took my 10x60 binoculars out to see what could be seen in my (new)
        neighborhood. The sky conditions were decent: clear and probably as dark as it gets
        around here. There was a waxing crescent moon in the southwest but it was not a major
        source of light and it was also partly obscured by clouds.</xhtml:p>

      <xhtml:p>The Orion Nebula gave a nice view (as always) in the binoculars. However, I saw
        no evidence of NGC-2024 and I recall seeing that in my binoculars when I lived in
        Tunbridge (on a very dark night). The Auriga clusters M-37, M-36, and M-38 all gave nice
        views. M-35 in Gemini was also nice. NGC-7789 in Cassiopeia was also visible but not
        spectacularly so.</xhtml:p>

      <xhtml:p>I spent some time scanning for comet C/2013 US 10 Catalina which is supposed to
        be near naked eye brightness around now. I didn't see it. On the other hand I didn't
        have a good finder chart with me and, after later consulting the chart in Guy Ottewell's
        Astronomical Calendar, I could see that was focused on slightly the wrong area. Also
        there was some haze to the north that may have inhibited the view as well.</xhtml:p>
    </text>
  </entry>

</entry-set>
