<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../AOML/AOML.xsl"?>

<observation-set xmlns="http://vortex.cis.vtc.edu/xml/AOML_0.0"
  xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://vortex.cis.vtc.edu/xml/AOML_0.0 ../AOML/AOML.xsd">

  <location>
    <value>
      <lat-long-alt>+43.00-072.50+300</lat-long-alt>
    </value>
    <notes>
      <xhtml:p>US-Vermont-Tunbridge</xhtml:p>
    </notes>
  </location>
  <observer>Peter C. Chapin</observer>
  <equipment>
    <notes>
      <xhtml:p>Unless otherwise stated, these observations were all made with my 75mm Unitron
        refractor using the 25mm eyepiece (48x).</xhtml:p>
    </notes>
  </equipment>
  <object>
    <name>W Her</name>
    <id catalog="AAVSO" id="1631+37"/>
    <type>star/variable</type>
    <constellation>Her</constellation>
  </object>
  <notes>
    <xhtml:p>This variable is a long period, "Mira" variable. Ideally I would observe it once
      every one or two weeks. Thus I should be able to follow this object despite the weather by
      working around periods of poor viewing. However, this variable has a range that exceeds
      what I can see in my telescope so I will loose track of it when it goes through its
      minimum. Also I can't track it effectively in binoculars (except, perhaps, when it is near
      maximum).</xhtml:p>

    <xhtml:p>Note that I attempt to record datetime information to the nearest five or ten
      minutes or so. Although such precision is unnecessary for such a long period variable, the
      accurate time information will make it easier for you to corrolate these observations with
      my sky conditions observations (stored separately).</xhtml:p>
  </notes>

  <observation>
    <datetime resolution="PT15M">
      <ISO>2003-06-16T03:10:00Z</ISO>
    </datetime>
    <notes>
      <xhtml:p>This was my first "real" observation of a variable star. I enjoyed making it so
        hopefully it won't be my last. I used the AAVSO's b-scale chart (downloaded from
          <xhtml:a href="http://www.aavso.org">www.aavso.org</xhtml:a>). It took me a little
        time to find the precise location of the variable but I didn't have any particular
        problems with it. I found it easiest to work from Eta Her. The star's brightness
        appeared between the 11.3 and 10.7 magnitude comparison stars. It was a bit closer to
        the 10.7. I am recording my magnitude estimate as <xhtml:b>10.9</xhtml:b>. Note that I
        needed to use averted vision to clearly see the variable and its comparison stars. At
        the time that I made the observation there was some moonlight moving into the
      area.</xhtml:p>
    </notes>
  </observation>

  <observation>
    <datetime resolution="PT15M">
      <ISO>2003-06-29T03:30:00Z</ISO>
    </datetime>
    <notes>
      <xhtml:p>I found estimating this variable to be quite tricky (due, no doubt to my
        inexperience with variable stars). I needed to use averted vision to see the variable
        well and to see the comparison stars. However, because the degree of averted vision can
        greatly impact the apparent brightness of a star I needed to be sure to view each star
        using the same amount of averted vision. I found this difficult. At times, for example,
        the 11.3 comparison star seemed brighter to me than the 10.7 comparison star. Under such
        conditions estimating a brightness to 0.1 magnitudes seemed hopeless. I can see that
        doing this well will require practice!</xhtml:p>

      <xhtml:p>In any case W appeared similar to the 10.1 comparison star tonight (perhaps a bit
        fainter). It was definitely not as bright as the 9.5 comparison star. I am recording my
        magnitude estimate as <xhtml:b>10.2</xhtml:b> but I feel that it could be substaintially
        off---perhaps more than 0.5 magnitudes either way.</xhtml:p>
    </notes>
  </observation>

  <observation>
    <datetime resolution="PT05M">
      <ISO>2003-07-10T03:35:00Z</ISO>
    </datetime>
    <notes>
      <xhtml:p>The variable was definitely brighter than the magnitude 9.5 comparison star,
        although not a lot brighter. It was not nearly as bright as the magnitude 8.4 or 8.5
        comparison stars. I am recording my estimate as <xhtml:b>9.3</xhtml:b>.</xhtml:p>

      <xhtml:p>Note that there was a considerable amount of moonlight in the region this
        evening.</xhtml:p>
    </notes>
  </observation>

</observation-set>
