<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../AOML/AOML.xsl"?>

<observation-set xmlns="http://vortex.cis.vtc.edu/xml/AOML_0.0"
  xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://vortex.cis.vtc.edu/xml/AOML_0.0 ../AOML/AOML.xsd">

  <location>
    <value>
      <lat-long-alt>+43.00-072.50+300</lat-long-alt>
    </value>
    <notes>
      <xhtml:p>US-Vermont-Tunbridge</xhtml:p>
    </notes>
  </location>
  <observer>Peter C. Chapin</observer>
  <equipment>
    <notes>
      <xhtml:p>Unless otherwise stated, these observations were all made with my Celestron 10x60
        binoculars.</xhtml:p>
    </notes>
  </equipment>
  <object>
    <name>X Cyg</name>
    <id catalog="AAVSO" id="2039+35"/>
    <type>star/variable</type>
    <constellation>Cyg</constellation>
  </object>
  <notes>
    <xhtml:p>This variable is a Cephid. It varies relatively quickly so that ideally
      observations should be made on a daily basis. However, this variable has the advantage of
      being fairly bright. I am able to follow its entire range and see all of its comparison
      stars readily in the binoculars. Thus I can make observations of this object quickly even
      on nights when I don't bring my telescope out.</xhtml:p>

    <xhtml:p>There aren't enough observations in this observation set to produce a reasonable
      light curve. I will try again another year. (Producing a reasonable light curve for a
      variable such as this one seems like a good goal for a novice variable star
    observer.)</xhtml:p>
  </notes>

  <observation>
    <datetime resolution="PT10M">
      <ISO>2003-07-02T03:30:00Z</ISO>
    </datetime>
    <notes>
      <xhtml:p>The variable looks very similar to, and perhaps a bit fainter than, the magnitude
        6.6 comparison star. The magnitude 6.5 and 6.4 comparison stars do seem slightly
        brighter. The magnitude 6.2 and 5.9 comparison stars are significantly brighter.
        However, the 6.9 comparison star seems somewhat fainter. To summarize, the variable
        appears to be between the 6.6 and 6.9 stars, closer to the 6.6 end. I'm recording my
        observed magnitude at <xhtml:b>6.7</xhtml:b>.</xhtml:p>
    </notes>
  </observation>

  <observation>
    <datetime resolution="PT10M">
      <ISO>2003-07-03T02:35:00Z</ISO>
    </datetime>
    <notes>
      <xhtml:p>The variable looks very much the same as it did last night. Its brightness is
        quite close to the magnitude 6.6 comparison star. I feel compelled to record it as
          <xhtml:b>6.6</xhtml:b> tonight.</xhtml:p>
    </notes>
  </observation>

  <observation>
    <datetime resolution="PT10M">
      <ISO>2003-07-05T02:35:00Z</ISO>
    </datetime>
    <notes>
      <xhtml:p>The variable is considerably brighter than the magnitude 6.6 comparison star
        tonight. It seems like it is between the 6.2 star and the 5.9 star, perhaps closer to
        the 6.2 star. I am recording it at <xhtml:b>6.1</xhtml:b> tonight. I notice that T Cyg
        (in the vicinity) is quite bright tonight.</xhtml:p>
    </notes>
  </observation>

  <observation>
    <datetime resolution="PT05M">
      <ISO>2003-07-10T02:55:00Z</ISO>
    </datetime>
    <notes>
      <xhtml:p>The variable is a bit brighter than the magnitude 6.6 comparison star and very
        similar to the magnitude 6.5 comparison star. I am recording it at
        <xhtml:b>6.5</xhtml:b> tonight.</xhtml:p>
    </notes>
  </observation>

  <observation>
    <datetime resolution="PT10M">
      <ISO>2003-07-15T03:35:00Z</ISO>
    </datetime>
    <notes>
      <xhtml:p>The variable was between the magnitude 6.9 and the magnitude 6.6 comparison
        stars. It seemed to be closer to the 6.9 star. I am recording it at
        <xhtml:b>6.8</xhtml:b> tonight.</xhtml:p>
    </notes>
  </observation>

  <observation>
    <datetime resolution="PT10M">
      <ISO>2003-07-26T03:25:00Z</ISO>
    </datetime>
    <notes>
      <xhtml:p>It has been a long time since my last observation. However, the delay was due
        almost entirely to an amazing amount of bad weather.</xhtml:p>

      <xhtml:p>The variable was distinctly brighter than the magnitude 6.6 comparison star. It
        appeared close to the magnitude 6.5 comparison star. I am recording it at
        <xhtml:b>6.5</xhtml:b> tonight.</xhtml:p>
    </notes>
  </observation>

</observation-set>
